（小西寛一(こにしかんいち)）あっ
（水戸(みと)郁魅(いくみ)）おい
食戟(しょくげき)
やろうぜ
（郁魅）ああん？
（小西）うう… ううっ
（郁魅）あたしと やんのか？
やんねえのか？
So? You gonna do it with me or what?
Hm?
Let's do it.
A Cooking Battle.
（幸平創真(ゆきひらそうま)のいびき）
Good morning, Souma-kun.
（一色慧(いっしきさとし)）おはよう 創真君
ふがっ
I'd like your help with something.
（一色）
ちょっと手伝ってほしいんだ
着替えたら出てきてくれないか
Can you get dressed and come outside?
I'm dead tired because I was up all night.
昨日 夜更かししてて眠いから
他を当たってくださいっす
Please ask someone else.
Oh, don't be like that.
そんなこと言わずに
That's where you were?!
そこにいたのかよ！
The Meat Invader
（吉野悠姫(よしのゆうき)）アッハハハ！
幸平も起こされたの？
He woke you up too, Yukihira?
（創真）吉野もか　俺ら
何の手伝いするわけ？
Yup, same as you.
So what did he drag us out of bed for?
（創真）あーふ…
（悠姫）裏の畑で野菜の収穫
We're harvesting veggies from the garden out back.
Wow, you guys even grow your own produce?
ああ すげえなぁ
食材作りまでやるなんてさ
"The road to good food is paved
with good ingredients."
おいしい料理への道は
いい食材から
That's our dorm's motto!
（悠姫）
それが うちの寮のモットーでね
Ibusaki prepares all of the wood
that he uses for smoking.
（悠姫）
伊武崎(いぶさき)は ああやって―
燻製(くんせい)に使うスモークウッドを
自作しちゃうし
Ryouko, who specializes in dishes using rice malt,
涼子は麹(こうじ)を使った料理が得意で―
has her own work space for fermentation.
専用の作業場を持ってるし
I want to create a special Polar Star chicken, like the Bresse chicken from France,
私もね フランスのブレス鶏(どり)みたく
極星鶏(きょくせいどり)とか作りたくてさ
so I'm breeding cage-free chickens out here.
放し飼いして
育ててるんだよね
（創真）へえ～
Really?
Last but not least...
（悠姫）そんでえ―
There's a plot that we take care of,
overseen by Isshiki-senpai.
一色先輩を中心に
運営してるのが―
Here it is!
We grow over ten kinds of vegetables in this field!
（悠姫）
十数種類の野菜が実る農園
Good morning, Souma-kun and Yoshino-kun!
おはよう！　創真君 吉野君
Morning labor is good for the spirit!
（一色）
朝の労働は
心を健やかにしてくれるよ
Let's sweat together!
共に汗を流そう
It fits him to a T!
似合う！
Knowing how food grows
is part of our training.
食材が どのように実るのか
知ることも―
料理の勉強の１つなんだ
You could call this the Polar Star Farm,
ここのことは 極星畑―
or perhaps even the Isshiki Farm.
もしくは 一色畑と呼んでくれて
構わないよ
Uh, sure.
Oh, Souma-kun!
（田所恵(たどころめぐみ)）創真君
（創真）あ…
You're here too, Tadokoro?
（創真）おお！　田所も来てたのか
Look!
ほら　一色先輩が育てた野菜
おいしそうでしょ？
Isshiki-senpai grew these vegetables.
Don't they look delicious?
Y'know, seeing you here in normal
clothing is very soothing.
何つーか
ホッとする似合い方だな
Yeah, Megumi's a breath of
fresh air at Polar Star.
うん　恵は極星の清涼剤だね
Here.
ほら　１つ かじってごらん
Why don't you try one?
Oh, thanks.
（創真）ああ どうも
Delicious!
うんま～！
It's plump and super sweet.
（創真）
張りがあって すげえ甘え！
I'd love to have these for our restaurant.
うちの実家で
仕入れたいくらいっすよ
How'd you grow something of this caliber?
よくこんな品質を
Oh, I spend all my time here.
（一色）いやあ もう
正直かかりっきりさ
I've been missing a lot of my classes lately.
おかげで最近
まともに授業に出てないんだ
Don't you have your priorities backwards?
（創真）本末転倒な気がする
Sorry to keep you guys waiting!
（榊涼子(さかきりょうこ)）お待たせー
（悠姫）ああ… わあ～
（創真）さあ どれにするかな
（恵）わあ
（創真）よし これだ
Whoa!
（創真）
おっほほ　これもうまそう！
This is delicious too!
（恵）もう～
創真君 食べてばっかり
C'mon, Souma-kun, all you're doing is eating!
（涼子）ホント
（創真）いいじゃねえか
Aw, come on.
みんなー 朝ごはんですよー！
Breakfast time, everyone!
（悠姫･涼子）わあ～
（創真）腰いてっ
My back's killing me.
I'm starving!
（悠姫）おなか減ったねー
（涼子）うん
おっ！　田所が作ったのか？
Tadokoro, you made these?
Yeah. You must be hungry.
（恵）うん おなかすいたでしょ？
どうぞ
Dig right in.
Wow.
わあ～
I see.
なるほど　田所ちゃん特製
３種のおにぎり… だね
It's the Tadokoro-chan Special, the Rice Ball Trio.
Awesome, rice balls would hit the spot after all that fieldwork!
いいね いいね！
畑仕事の後のおにぎり！
Thanks for the food!
いっただきまーす！
あむ
ああー！　おいしい！
So delicious!
これ ねぎ塩ダレだね
There's green onions and salt in this, right?
You seasoned cooked chicken tenderloin with it
and also brushed some onto the rice ball!
さっとゆでた鶏ささみに
ねぎ塩ダレをあえて―
おにぎり表面にも
タレが塗ってある
The saltiness really excites your appetite!
塩っけが食欲をそそるわぁ～
体動かすと
塩味が恋しくなるのよね
Salty foods are so appealing
after doing manual labor.
This must be kelp.
これは昆布か
おにぎりの定番だね
It's a classic rice ball ingredient.
あむ　うん…
（一色）
うん！　昆布の佃煮(つくだに)と…チーズ？
Kelp simmered in soy sauce and cheese?
Right!
はい　佃煮の こってりした甘さが
チーズに意外と合うんです
The strong sweet flavor of the kelp pairs surprisingly well with the cheese.
So what's the last one?!
じゃあ ラストは何だ？
あむっ
Delicious!
（創真）
うんめ～！
ニンニクの風味が たまんねえ！
The garlic flavor rocks!
This one's pork marinated with garlic.
これはね 豚肉のニンニク漬け
Wow!
へーえ！
After seeing you use honey in class the other day,
（恵）こないだ授業で 創真君が
ハチミツ使ってたのを見て―
I decided to try something based on that.
私なりに工夫してみたんだ
I marinated boiled boneless pork rib in a mixture of garlic, miso, sake, and honey.
ゆでた豚バラ肉を―
ニンニクとお味噌(みそ)とお酒
ハチミツを混ぜた物に漬け込んだの
It goes really well with rice,
ご飯と すっごく合うから―
so I chopped it up and made rice balls with it!
細かく切って
おにぎりに入れたんだ
Huh.
Oh, there's barley and roasted green tea as well.
あ　麦茶と ほうじ茶もあるから
好きなほうをどうぞ
Please have whichever you'd like.
（悠姫）わあ～
（涼子）最高！
Sigh...
（５人）ほう…
This is the appeal of Tadokoro-chan's cooking.
これが田所ちゃんの料理の
魅力だね
It's comfort food that soothes everyone's souls.
（一色）食べる者の心を
穏やかにしてくれる
The chicken is moist,
ささみはパサついてねえし
豚肉もバッチリ柔らか
and the pork's nice and tender too.
Both bear the hallmarks of careful preparation.
どれも丁寧に
仕事がしてあるなぁ
えっへへ
So why can't you cook like this in class?
何で これが
授業で できねえんだ？
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
はうっ！
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
STAB
Why can't you cook
like this in class?
I've always had issues with stage fright.
私 昔から あがり症で―
When I get nervous, I blank out,
緊張すると頭が真っ白になって
失敗ばかりしちゃって…
and then I fail at everything.
ああ 大変だなぁ
Oh, that's tough.
You should try to be more relaxed when you cook, Tadokoro-chan.
（一色）
もっとリラックスして
調理することだよ 田所ちゃん
Yeah, Megumi.
（悠姫）
うんうん　恵は いい料理人と
いいお嫁さん どっちもなれるよ
You'd make a good cook and a good wife.
（恵）あっ…
えっへへ そうかな～？
You think so?
Huh?
（創真）
え？　研究会？
Research societies?
Yeah. Tohtsuki has lots of groups
that study various foods and cuisines.
テーマごとに料理を研究する会が
遠月(とおつき)には いっぱいあるの
For instance, some groups
develop new recipes after school.
例えば 放課後みんなで
新しいメニューを開発したり
Or they can compete in cooking
contests outside of the academy.
学外の料理コンテストに
参加したりとかね
You could say it's Tohtsuki's
version of school clubs.
普通の学校で言えば
部活動みたいな感じかな
I'm in the Regional Cooking Research Society.
私は 郷土料理研究会に
入ってるんだ～
Huh.
ふ～ん
You weren't kidding.
（創真）ホントだ　和洋中
宮廷料理に精進料理
Asian and Western cuisine.
Imperial court and Buddhist cuisines.
発酵食に保存食
Fermentation and preservation.
Oh, this one's for train bentos!
（創真）ああ　こっちは駅弁
Donburi Research Society
Huh?
ん？　丼物(どんもの)研究会？
Donburi Research Society
The Donburi Research Society?
店のメニューの
参考になるかも
Maybe I'll find inspiration for our restaurant's menu.
All right, guess I'll go take a look.
よし 見学すっか
Let's go, Tadokoro!
（創真）行くぞ 田所
Huh?
（恵）あ？　私も？
Donburi Research Society
I'm coming with you?
This is...
Doom Gloom
Sorry, but you should probably go.
悪(わり)いけど帰りな
Doom Gloom
Don RS is about to become history.
もうじき丼研は
つぶされる運命だからよぉ
Doom Gloom
What?!
You said you're Yukihira and Tadokoro?
（小西）
幸平と田所って言ったか？
Konishi Kan'ichi
High School, 2nd Year
The Don of Don RS
Doom Gloom
I'm Konishi, the leader of this research society.
俺は小西
ここの主将を張ってる者だ
Doom Gloom
You okay, Senpai?
大丈夫すか 先輩
何か しおしおしてますけど
You look pretty down.
（小西）ヘッ ヘヘ　笑えばいいさ
丼研を守れない俺なんか
Mock me all you want.
I couldn't save Don RS.
Don RS
Are these recipe collections?
これ レシピ集？
It's full of recipes created by Don RS.
（恵）丼研で考えた
メニューみたいだよ
Let's take a look.
From more mainstream items to offbeat ones,
王道メニューから変わり種まで
どれもピリッとした工夫がある
these dishes are jazzed up with a spark of creativity.
These recipes are all interesting!
どのレシピも
おもしれえじゃん
Why are you shutting down?
何で ここ
つぶされなきゃいけねえの？
（小西）んん… だあ！
（恵）あああっ
Rising
You understand?
（小西）分かってくれるかぁ～
（恵）ひいっ！
Rising
Yukihira!
（小西）幸平ぁ～！
（創真）泣いてる
He's crying!
（小西）丼とは
早い 旨い 安いの様式美
The don has a functional beauty that obeys the laws of speed, taste, and affordability!
Speed
Taste
Affordability
It's so manly you can eat it completely with one arm!
ひと椀(わん)で完結する男らしさ！
It's food for men who fight!
戦う男のための男飯！
I...
俺は… 俺は一匹の男として―
As a man...
AHHHHHH
I cannot die until I've created the ultimate don!
丼を極めるまでは
死ねないんだぁ～！
AHHHHHH
He really is something.
何か すごい人だね
He's kind of oppressive.
イヤ～な暑苦しさがあるな
俺の丼研…
My Don RS!
If only Nakiri Erina didn't exist!
薙切えりなさえ いなければ
Nakiri?
薙切？
Right, this is how she works.
ああ　奴のやり口は こうだ
まずは 気に入らない団体の
予算カットや部室の縮小を―
First, she'll propose that the council slash the budget or allotted space
for any group she doesn't like.
会議に提出
強引に可決させる
She coerces them into voting her way.
Once a group is cornered,
it's left with only one choice:
ジリ貧になった相手に
残された手は１つしかない
the last-ditch Cooking Battle!
（小西）一発逆転の食戟だ
（創真）あ…
Cooking
Battle
（小西）
薙切は食戟を受けることを
のむ代わりに―
In exchange for accepting the challenge,
Nakiri will make even more extreme demands.
さらに無茶な要求を
突きつけ―
In the end, she'll get what she wants.
最終的には
丸ごと自分の望むままに
That is how she expands her sphere of influence.
そうやって
勢力を広げ続けてるんだ
Once my members learned that our opponent is one of Nakiri's lackeys,
丼研の部員たちは
今回の相手が―
Konishi Kan'ichi
薙切の手先だと
知った途端 全員…
Konishi Kan'ichi
Donburi Research Society Member List
they all fled.
Konishi Kan'ichi
Donburi Research Society Member List
（終了ゴング）
（小西）逃げ出しやがった…
He couldn't inspire a loyal following, huh?
（創真）
この先輩 人望ねえ～
So are you facing off against Nakiri?
あ… んで
対戦相手は薙切なのか？
It's—
（小西）あ そらあ…
（ドアが開く音）
（小西）え… おい！
Hey!
Rather than renovating,
（作業員）
やはり改装するより 完全に崩して
建て直すほうが早いかと
it'd be faster to raze this place
and rebuild from scratch.
Yeah?
（郁魅）そう　じゃあ それで
Then let's do that.
Who do you think you are, Mito?!
何のつもりだよ 水戸！
What? I'm just checking this place out.
（郁魅）何って
早めの下見に来たんだよ
I already know the outcome, after all.
結果は もう見えてるからさぁ
Like Erina-sama said,
えりな様も
おっしゃってたよ
Mito Ikumi
High School, 1st Year
no matter how much effort you put into a don,
〝丼なんて―〞
〝いくらこだわっても
しょせん―〞
it's a low-class dish relegated to class B gourmet fare.
〝Ｂ級グルメでしかない
低俗な品〞
"Tohtsuki has no need for such a dish," she said.
“この遠月には必要ありません”
…てね　フフッ
Well, it's a different story
if you think you can beat me.
まあ あたしに
勝つ自信があるなら―
話は別だけどなぁ
Get it now, Mr. RS leader?
（郁魅）分かったかい 主将さん
A club like this doesn't belong here.
お呼びじゃないのさ
こんな部は
あ… くうっ…
Niku (meat) Mi
Damn you, Nikumi.
肉魅(にくみ)が
Niku (meat) Mi
My name isn't Nikumi.
肉魅じゃねえ
もう一度 言ったら…
If you ever call me that again...
Wait, she's your Cooking Battle opponent?
まさか あの人が
食戟の相手？
Who the hell's she?
何なの あいつ
She's Mito Ikumi-san,
水戸郁魅さん
also known as the Meat Master.
ミートマスターの
異名を持つ料理人
Ever since junior high,
she's always received high ratings.
中等部から
いつも上位の成績で―
And she's never received anything below an A rating for meat dishes.
特に肉料理の授業では Ａ評価しか
取ったことがないっていう すご腕
Her knowledge of all things meat is said to be top-notch, even within the academy.
肉への造詣(ぞうけい)の深さは
学園トップクラスとか
All ingredients must bow before worthy meat!
価値ある肉に
全ての食材は ひれ伏す
No matter what dish you may try to create,
あんたが
どんな品を作ろうと―
あたしの超高級肉には
勝てねえんだよ
you will never beat my super high-quality meat!
I think you give cooking a bad name if all you care about is the price of your ingredients.
食材の値段だけで喜んでちゃ
料理人の名折れだと思うぜ
ああん？
Senpai...
（創真）先輩 この食戟―
would you let me handle this Cooking Battle?
俺に任せてくんねえかな
Who the hell are you?
何だよ あんた
部外者は引っ込んで… あっ
Outsiders should butt out.
Wait, you're that transfer student from the opening ceremony.
（郁魅）
あんた 編入生？　始業式の
あんたとは
話してみたかったんだ
I've been wanting to talk to you.
You must have a lot of confidence in your skills
他人の食戟に
しゃしゃり出ようとするなんて―
随分 腕に自信があるんだね
if you're butting into someone else's Cooking Battle.
Why don't we compete on your turf with a meat dish?
何なら そっちの土俵
肉料理対決でもいいけど
I'll win, though.
（創真）俺 勝つし
Then if I win, asshole,
（郁魅）んじゃ てめえ―
あたしに負けたら―
are you willing to leave Tohtsuki?
遠月から出ていくか？
ケッ　その度胸もねえなら
デカい口たたくんじゃあ…
If you don't have the balls
to do that, don't talk so big.
Sure, fine!
（創真）ああ いいぜ
What?!
（郁魅）何？
In return, if I win...
その代わり 俺が勝ったら…
Yeah, you'll have to join Don RS.
ああ そうだなぁ
お前 丼研入れ
Huh?
Huh?!
Join Don RS and contribute
to advancing donburi culture.
丼研入って
丼文化の発展に貢献しろ
Call it penance for bothering us.
迷惑かけた わびってことで
You really think you can beat me?
本気で あたしに勝つ気かよ
It's quitting time for all you contractors!
業者の皆さーん 今日は撤収
（作業員たち）失礼します
I'll cut you some slack with the theme.
じゃあ お題のほうは
そっちに譲歩してやるよ
The main ingredient will be meat,
メイン食材は肉　作る品目は丼
and the dish will be the don.
The cook-off will be in three days!
開戦は３日後だ
Why'd you do that, Yukihira?
幸平 どうして？
Oh.
She kept going on about how
pricey meat is everything,
高い肉が全てってのは―
and I couldn't let that pass
because I'm a diner brat.
定食屋の せがれとして
聞き捨てならねえし―
Besides, I think this club's
too good to let it go to waste.
何より この場所
つぶすには惜しいと思ったからね
Yukihira!
幸平…
But how are you going to beat her, Souma-kun?
でも 創真君
何か勝算はあるの？
I'll think of something.
え 今から考える
ああ～ やっぱりぃ！
I knew it!
I'm grateful to Erina-sama
for letting me handle this.
（郁魅）
この仕事を任せてくれた
えりな様に感謝だねぇ
I'll teach that uppity transfer student
the pleasure of the flesh.
調子こいた編入生に
肉の快感を教えてやる
It's heavier
than I thought...
A bit more to the right. Just a bit more.
A little bit more.
What was Yukihira thinking?!
（悠姫）
幸平の奴 何考えてんの？
To Sports
Transfer Student to Be in a Cooking Battle
His Opponent is the Meat Master, Mito Ikumi!
Everyone in the academy's talking about it!
学園中 もう超ウワサに
なってるよぉ！
（悠姫）うん～
（涼子）悠姫 落ち着いて
Calm down, Yuuki!
私も精一杯 手伝うけど
でも 本番まで時間なさすぎだよ
I'll do my best to help,
but there's just too little time!
So what will you do, Souma-kun?
（一色）
さて どう出る？　創真君
Cooking Battle
T-minus 2 Days
Strategy Session
Theme:
Don
Meat
Ingredient:
Since last night,
（小西）あれから一晩 俺も
じっくり考えてみた
Strategy Session
Theme:
Don
Meat
Ingredient:
I've been giving this a lot of thought.
Nikumi's a specialist in meat,
肉魅は肉…
特に牛肉のスペシャリストだ
beef in particular.
So, I don't think we should use beef.
だったら こっちは
牛(ぎゅう)に こだわることはねえと思う
For example, maybe we could
do a chicken-and-egg don.
例えば 親子丼だって鶏肉
今回のテーマに合うんだ
Chicken still fits the theme.
We should differentiate ourselves from Nikumi as much as possible.
（小西）できるだけ肉魅と
かぶらない品のほうがいい
I see. An offbeat choice.
なるほど
なるべく変わり種か
What kind of don do you like, Tadokoro?
田所は
好きな丼とかあるか？
Well, it's not a traditional don,
and it's not meat-based,
ええっと 丼って言えるか
分からないし―
お肉でもないけど
but I like taking scallops that've been lightly grilled in the shell
ホタテをね 網であぶって
開いたところに―
バターと しょうゆを
ちょっぴり流し込むの
and seasoning them with a bit of butter and soy sauce.
They're godly on piping hot rice!
それをホカホカのご飯に
のせて食べるのが おいしいんだ～
You're right.
そうだよ
海鮮丼って手もあったのに―
We could've gone with a seafood don,
Doom Gloom
but you just had to go ahead
and say we'd do meat.
幸平が 肉で勝負するとか
言うから…
It's a done deal. Quit complaining!
もう勝負内容は
決まったんだから―
グジグジすんなよなぁ
You don't know how strong Nikumi is!
お前は 肉魅の強さを
分かってねえんだ！
If we get slammed with
her A5 beef, we're done for!
もしＡ５の牛肉でも
出されたりしたら 勝ち目はねえ
English
"Eigo"?
英語？　イングリッシュ？
English
English?
By A5 you mean the grade of beef, right?
Ａ５って確か
牛肉の質を決めるランクですよね
ああ そうだ
Yeah, that's right.
The "A" is the yield grade, which is based on how much of a carcass is actually beef!
（小西）
解体した牛から取れる肉重量の
割合を示す―
歩留(ぶど)まり等級！
That ranges from A to C!
それがＡからＣの３段階
Then the firmness and texture of the meat,
サシの量 肉の締まりとキメ
脂肪の光沢など―
the luster of the fat, and so on
Luster
Texture
determine the quality grade,
あらゆる条件からの肉質等級！
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
Marbling
Firmness
Luster
Texture
which ranges from 1 to 5!
それが５から１の５段階
Only beef that meets the highest qualifications for both grades
（小西）
この両方で最高ランクを
獲得した牛肉
receives the A5 rating!
それがＡ５と言うわけだ
I've eaten one of Nikumi's steaks at an academy event.
俺は学園の行事で―
肉魅の焼いたステーキを
食ったことがある
At... At that level...
あの…
あのレベルの肉は―
you can drink the meat!
Drink it
飲める！
Drink it?!
（恵）ええ？
（創真）飲める？
That's right!
そう　噛(か)んだ瞬間
肉から旨味の塊へと変化し―
The moment you bite into it,
the beef transforms into a mass of umami that glides down your throat.
喉をつるんと通り抜けていく
If you were to order that
kind of meat at any store,
あんな肉 店で注文したら
諭吉が何枚も飛んでいくだろうよ
you'd have to throw down several Benjamins.
And there's something else
that you have to keep in mind.
そして
これも重要な点だが―
Any ingredient you use in a Cooking Battle...
食戟に使う食材の全ては―
you must prepare yourself.
当事者が自ら
用意しなければならない
Procuring ingredients is considered an essential skill for chefs!
素材の調達も
料理人の技量の１つだからだ
The Mito family operates a large-scale meat wholesale business.
水戸一族は 大規模な肉の卸し業を
展開してて―
They have the market cornered
when it comes to premium beef.
牛肉業界の一角を牛耳っている
They have the finances,
the facilities, and the distribution.
資金力 設備力 流通ルート
All of this lies behind Nikumi's
premium-quality cooking...
これら全てが 肉魅の最高品質の
料理を構築してるわけだ…
Doom Gloom
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
U
n
g
u
a
r
d
e
He's bringing himself down with his own talk.
自分で しゃべりながら
しおれてる
Can we really beat meat like that?
そんなすごいお肉を
超えるなんて―
本当に できるのかな？
Y'know...
（創真）あのさ
（恵）ん？
You know what?
でも やっぱり
丼研も牛肉でいこう
Don RS should go with beef too.
Huh?!
はあ？　おい 幸平
俺の話 聞いてたか？
Look here, Yukihira.
Were you even listening to me?
We don't have a snowball's chance in—
牛じゃ到底 肉魅には…
小西先輩も言ったじゃん
You said it yourself, Konishi-senpai.
The don is about speed, taste, and affordability.
丼は早い 旨い 安いだって
Nikumi's making fun of that maxim.
肉魅は
それをバカにしたんだぜ
If we're to make her respect the don,
丼を認めさせるには―
we have to win with a fast and easy beef dish!
牛肉のお手頃メニューで勝たなきゃ
意味ないでしょ！
（小西）んっ…
（創真）あと変に高級食材―
Also, we can't use super premium ingredients.
使うのもナシな
丼の魅力は そこじゃねえもん
That's not where the don shines.
A-At times, men must compromise their principles in order to win.
と… 時に男は己の信念を
曲げてでも守るべきものが…
Okay.
うん　じゃ 早速買い出しだ
Let's go shopping.
（小西）うお え… いや…
How much do you have left in Don RS's budget?
丼研の部費って
あといくら残ってんの？
Doom Gloom
W-Well...
そ… それが…
Huh?
（創真）たったこれだけ？
That's it?
I'll just have to chip in from my personal funds!
（創真）俺の生活費から
用立てるしかねえ！
This is all I have?!
残高 こんだけえー？
（ＡＴＭの音声）
ありがとうございました
Thank you for your business.
I'll send you some money to live on.
（幸平城一郎(ゆきひらじょういちろう)）
お前の生活費は
適当に振り込むから
This is what "some" meant?
（創真）
え… 適当って そういうこと？
そういう意味の適当？
That's what you meant?
Doom
This is rough.
これは ちょっと―
Doom
Donburi Research Society
I might be in trouble.
ヤバいかも…
（小西）ええい
（創真）あ…
（小西）丼研の過去のレシピ集だ
（恵）あ… はっ はっ はっ…
These are Don RS's recipe
collections from the past.
You might find something useful in there.
使えるものが
あるかもしれねえ
Senpai, I found some more of them.
先輩 これも
（小西）おお サンキュー
その束 こっちに
Oh, thanks!
Put that stack over there.
All right!
よし　やりますか！
Let's do this!
All done!
（創真）上がり　味見 頼んます
Have a taste, please!
A cutlet don, subbing in beef for pork!
豚の代わりに牛肉を使った
ビフカツ丼
I changed the Don RS recipe by using a mix of chicken and quail eggs,
丼研レシピを
さらに工夫して―
鶏とうずらを混ぜた卵でとじたから
コクが深まったはず
so it should have a richer taste.
（小西）あむっ んっ んっ…
はふ～っ
It's not bad, but it's still not enough!
悪くはない　だが足りねえ
口に入れた時のインパクトが
There isn't enough impact in the first bite.
Nikumi's dishes always deliver
a punch in the mouth.
肉魅の品は こう
舌にガツンとくるんだよ
A punch, huh?
ガツンと…　なら脂だ
Then we're talking fat!
How about a sukiyaki don made with sugar and beef fat, all finished off with a chicken egg?
（創真）
砂糖と牛脂で焼き上げ
卵を落とした すき焼き丼！
あっふ
はふ～っ
This won't work, either.
（小西）いや ダメだ
上品な旨味が出てねえ！
The flavor's not refined enough!
（創真）じゃあ 牛脂を減らして
代わりに…
Okay, we can decrease the amount
of beef fat, and instead...
Um, how about this recipe?
（恵）あの こっちのレシピは
どうかな？
Cooking Battle
T-minus 1 Day
あむっ
ん あむっ
（小西）あむっ
Senpai's gone deathly pale again!
（恵）先輩がまた
真っ白に しおれてる！
Splash water on him to get him back!
水ぶっかけて起こせ！
We've followed all the promising leads in Don RS's recipe collection.
（創真）
丼研のレシピで目ぼしい品は
全て試しちまった
We've tried every single variation we could think of.
思いつく限り アレンジも加えた
Souma-kun, why don't you
go and get some rest?
（恵）創真君
少しだけでも休んだら？
Japanese-style Steakdon
Maybe you'll come up with something if you take a break,
気分を変えたら
この間の授業の時みたいな―
just like that day in class.
いいアイデアが
思いつくかも… なんて
Japanese-style Steakdon
Maybe.
Oh, like how I used honey
to tenderize the meat.
ああ～　ハチミツで肉を
柔らかくしたやつな
S-Souma-kun?
そ… 創真君？
I owe you one, Tadokoro!
助かったぜ 田所　あったわ
I've got an idea.
I think I know how to make
affordable meat sing!
値段が手頃な肉に
インパクトを与える方法
Konishi-san!
小西さん 部位はサーロインでも
ランプでも どこでもいい
It can be sirloin or even the rump!
（小西）あああ…
（創真）牛のステーキ肉―
Do you have any steaks left?
残ってるか？
Steaks?
牛ステーキ？
Slice a grid pattern into a steak,
（創真）
ステーキ肉に
格子状の切り込みを入れ―
then pound it out flat.
たたいて伸ばす
Spread minced onions on both sides of the meat, then let it rest.
みじん切りにした たまねぎを
肉の両面にまぶして しばらく置く
Remove the onions,
たまねぎを取り除いた肉に
塩とコショウで味つけ
then season the meat with salt and pepper.
Cook the steak in butter,
バターを溶かして 肉を焼く
then sauté the onions in the drippings.
その焼き汁と絡めるように
たまねぎをいためる
Onions...
たまねぎ？
Sprinkle the cooked onions on top of the meat, and it's done.
（創真）
肉の上に いためたたまねぎを
満遍なくのせて 完成だ
It's a Chaliapin steak!
これは
シャリアピンステーキ！
When the opera singer
Fyodor Chaliapin came to Japan,
（小西）
オペラ歌手 フョードル･
シャリアピンが―
来日した時
歯の痛みに悩まされ―
he was suffering from a toothache.
"May I have a tender steak?"
That request inspired this dish.
“柔らかいステーキが食べたい”と
要望したことで考案された―
It's an offbeat dish that can only be found in Japan!
海外には存在しねえ
日本独自の変わり種ステーキだ
All right, both of you try it.
さあ ２人とも味見を
O-Okay!
A'ight.
おう
So light!
It's so tender!
（小西）何て柔らかさだ
箸で簡単に割れる
You can easily cut it with chopsticks!
ん あむ… んん
And every time you bite into it...
そして 噛む度に口の中で…
...it dissolves in your mouth.
（恵･小西）ほぐれていく～
Onions have enzymes that tenderize proteins,
たまねぎにはタンパク質を分解する
酵素が含まれている
just like pineapples and honey.
パイナップルや
ハチミツみたいにね
That's why the meat is so tender.
だから ここまで
肉が柔らかくなるんだ
I wouldn't have guessed
that this was a cheap cut of beef.
（小西）安い肉とは思えねえ
My mouth's full of its flavor.
口の中が
うまさで満たされていく
And it goes without saying that it pairs well with rice.
ご飯との相性も申し分ねえ
But...
だが本当に これだけで―
will this really be enough...
to surpass Nikumi's A5 meat?
あの肉魅のＡ５級の肉に
勝てるのか？
I'll use Japanese Black wagyu fillet.
（郁魅）私が使うのは
黒毛和牛のフィレ肉
A5 grade, of course. Not only that,
等級は当然Ａ５
しかも それを
ひと月以上 熟成させ―
it'll have been aged over a month to be at its peak flavor the day it's served.
当日に最も旨い状態まで
仕上げます
In other words, it'll be an A5 to top all A5 beef.
（郁魅）
いわばＡ５を超えたＡ５
I'll cook it in a way that optimizes its taste,
その旨さを
最大に引き出す調理で―
and I'll crush the Don RS.
丼研なんて
サクッと つぶして見せますよ
I have high hopes.
（薙切(なきり)えりな）期待してます
（郁魅）
では 失礼します
Excuse me.
I didn't think an opportunity would come so soon.
（えりな）こんなに早く
機会が来るなんて
Yukihira Souma.
幸平創真　あなたを遠月から
追放するチャンスが
I will take this chance to purge you from Tohtsuki.
End
Next Episode
Next time on Shokugeki no Souma,
（郁魅）次回「食戟のソーマ」
７品目だぜ
the seventh dish:
Menu
The Quiet Don,
the Eloquent Don
The Quiet Don, the Eloquent Don.
「静かなる丼
雄弁な丼」
Enjoy.
味わいな
Ba-dum
What a demanding body you have!